Okay, this is Concord Storytellers, another episode after a hiatus for the summer.
And I'm excited to make a new friend, new neighbor, Rob Morrison.
Welcome.
Well, welcome to my house.
Thank you.
Thank you for having me over.
This is my first destination episode, so we're breaking down barriers and seeing more of
Concord.
I love that you are, I have to say, right in the thick of it here in Concord, a quick
walk to some of our most historic sites, a quick walk to the Colonial Line in downtown.
How long have you lived here?
Lived here, let's see, we're newcomers.
We've been here 33 years.
Okay.
Unless you're born here, you can't say you've been here a long time.
Yeah.
We moved here having lived in England for a couple of years.
We came back and we're looking for an apartment.
And I found a great apartment in Arlington with six rooms and a lot of space and it's
going to be fantastic.
And then we found this little tiny apartment in Concord and one bedroom, one and a half
bedrooms.
And I said, you know, six rooms, one room, what are you...
He goes, no, I'll be happy here.
She trumped it and I was wise enough to listen to her because we're very happy to have landed
in Concord, which has really quickly become our home.
Yeah.
I feel the same way.
I've been here for five years now.
We were similar, not Arlington, but we were looking in Belmont and Lexington after my
son was born.
And we met a realtor here who was showing us around those towns, but also here.
We kept coming back here saying, it's kind of a long commute into Boston, but it's just
so otherwise so perfect.
And in terms of the size of the town, the amount of land available, the historic presence,
just the feeling that we had when we were here.
So we were very glad to come here.
And it's nice to know that you were at once a newcomer too, probably younger than we were
when we moved out here, but you stayed.
What's been the draw to stay here?
Well, the kids went to the schools here, and I was working in various places around New
England in building materials and exporting building materials.
And then I turned 40 and it kind of hit me like a ton of bricks.
I said, I don't want to be doing this anymore.
I want to get back to teaching, which I had originally trained to be a teacher in college.
So I put together one cover letter and one resume and walked it down the street to the
Fenn School.
And I'm just an incredibly lucky guy.
I was zigging when everybody else was zagging, everybody else was going towards dot coms
and stock options and things like that.
I went low tech and then the bubble burst a year or two later and everybody wanted my
job.
I had it.
So then I started teaching at Fenn and I taught there for 23 years and had a wonderful time
teaching English and social studies.
That's fantastic.
And some drama.
Yeah.
And I mean, the school system here, I grew up in small town Tennessee, public school
system.
The school system here is incredible in terms of the options that students have here.
How does the Fenn School fit into the picture for Concord residents?
Well, it's all boys.
It's a strange age group.
It's fourth grade through ninth grade.
It's because there's a feeder school that goes K through three at Neshoba Brooks, which
is coed until that point.
So that's why there's a starting point in the fourth grade.
But it works for us.
Anybody who works there has to embrace middle school boy madness.
Okay.
You have that energy and have to be not overwhelmed by those difficult years.
Sure.
I expect to have some rough edges from the kids.
But they're really great boys and they buy into the ethos of the school pretty quickly.
Yeah, that's great.
So I met you through Richard Smith, local historian, and he had mentioned that you were
on this journey that started several years ago to discover all of the Concords in the
U.S.
Can you talk a little bit about that?
Sure.
So as a social studies teacher, I started to look more deeply into the history of Concord.
And I actually realized I could teach all of American history simply through the lens
of the history of the town of Concord.
So the deeper I got into looking at Concord, I'd look things up on the internet.
And there were these other towns named Concord.
I said, wow, I wonder what life is like there.
How did they get their name?
How many are there?
And I started accruing a list.
And eventually I got up to 50 different Concords, 60 different Concords, 70.
All in the U.S.?
I kept finding new ones.
Wow.
And I end up, right now I think I have 91 Concords that I've found so far.
And how many of those have you visited?
Is that the number you visited?
I visited about 70.
Wow.
So it's, I've still got 20 to go.
And it's, unfortunately they're kind of tough ones like Concord, Nebraska and Concord, South
Dakota, a couple in Missouri.
So these are like, these are like take a connecting flight somewhere and then drive five hours
kind of thing or?
Yeah, something like that.
Okay.
And how many?
I try to do a loop so that I can, I can catch a whole bunch of flights in one trip.
That's cool.
And how many, how many trips is the 70 been?
Well it started off with my daughter who was working in Arizona needing her car.
And so she said, okay, well you can fly home and drive your car back, but that's a long
drive for a young lady on her own.
So we said, well, maybe we'll drive the car.
Mom and I will drive the car out to you and then fly back.
So I said, well, maybe we'll just stop off for lunch at Concord, New York and Staten
Island.
Well, we'll spend the night in Concord, Pennsylvania.
Then the next morning we drove down to Concord, Concord, Virginia, then Concord, Tennessee,
Concord, Alabama, Concord, Louisiana by day three, Concord, Texas, two Concords in Texas.
And then, and then there were no more Concords to Arizona.
So then it was a straight run.
So what could have been a three or four day trip, three or four day trip on interstates
turned into a five, five day meander through different Concords.
That's cool.
I was, I was reading your, you have published about this online on your blog and you were
saying, I think it was after that first trip, you were saying you hadn't reached out to
these towns beforehand to find a guide or anyone to talk.
And so you were just, and you're also in this time crunch, you're kind of just going to
the random people and asking them about the town.
Definitely fully winging it.
What did that look like?
It was fun.
I mean, it had its own charm, but realized I got really lucky in Concord, Louisiana because
in Concord, Louisiana, there's no people there except on Sunday morning and Wednesday night
and Wednesday night's Bible night study.
No Bible study night, excuse me.
And I happened to be there during Bible study and I, and there were like six white pickup
trucks in front of the church and the one church that was in, which was at a crossroads
where there used to be a town of Concord.
So I knocked on the door and they let me in and I gave my spiel about what I was doing
and I had a great time at meetings.
That's great.
I remember seeing their church and hearing stories about their life in Concord, Louisiana.
That's cool.
But I realized how lucky I was and so I didn't want to depend on that kind of luck in the
future.
So I tried to be a lot more planful.
Having contacts and having guides or whatever I could get from what I could glean on the
internet.
Got it.
A lot of these places, you can't find anybody who's got a published email or anything.
There's certainly no like tourism department or anything like that.
No, I mean, it really, interestingly, the next trip I took was to this little honeypot
of Concords in Texas.
There were 13 Concords in East Texas alone and none of them had currently had a population
of more than 250 people.
That's incredible.
And none of them had heard of each other either.
They thought they were the only Concord, Texas for the most part.
For the most part.
Yeah.
And some of them, one of them was just a graveyard that was once a thriving town.
And the church had fallen down and everything was gone but there was still the graveyard
and there was a history to the town that I was able to uncover.
Really interesting one was one that was underneath the water reservoir, huge, second largest
water reservoir in Texas, which was kind of like Lake Quabon in Massachusetts.
One of those towns was Concord, Texas.
And when the water level is really, really low after drought, you can still see the steps
of the church rise up out of the reservoir.
And that's the only remnants of the town of Concord, Texas, except for all the roads
that go into it are all called like Concord Road or Concord View or all of these things.
But they're just kind of dead end in a lake.
That's fascinating.
Wow.
And I noticed, I mean I had to since I grew up in Tennessee, look at the Concord, Tennessee
entry.
And one, I had to laugh because you talk about teaching social studies through the lens of
Concord, Massachusetts.
I was taught American history in high school through the lens of a Southern Baptist preacher
who also called it in our class the War of the Northern Aggression.
And everyone just kind of looked, I remember that we were sophomores in high school and
we looked at, wait, is that correct?
But you also mentioned how much that town had changed from the Oak Ridge Project, I
think it was.
Tennessee Valley.
Oh, Tennessee, the TVA project from the 40s.
They had flooded the town.
So they had to move the graveyard from the river bank up on top of the hill.
They had to move a bunch of buildings up to the top.
So that's similar to that Texas town where the original town is underwater now.
Sort of.
Sort of, yeah.
This one survived.
And it's, I actually went back a second time because I hadn't had enough time to really
meet people there on that first trip.
And so I felt like I wanted to do it justice and meet some people.
And so I was able to reach out to some churchgoers.
And I got there on a Sunday morning and I'm not a religious person, but I've been to a
lot of church services going to this project.
This is where people gather.
Absolutely.
Especially in the South.
And I bet the story of you coming there is still told in those churches.
I used to go to those churches in Tennessee.
I'm telling you that like anytime someone comes that's an outsider, it's like the record
stops and it's just fascinating that there's someone new in the community.
Yeah, there's a really, there's a story I'm trying to piece together.
But there was this preacher who came down through the Cumberland Gap.
And he became a Cumberland Gap Presbyterian.
And he went down through the South and then went into East Texas.
And he was known for starting up all these small Presbyterian churches.
And this was during the time when Texas was Mexican territory.
And he became the personal preacher of, I think it was Sam Houston.
And anyway, this guy, I find out later his grandfather fought at the North Bridge.
No way.
He was from Massachusetts.
Huh.
And his father and his uncle both fought at the North Bridge.
Wow.
And I think he was one of the guys who was sprinkling these towns.
Because many of the towns were named Concord after Concord Baptist Churches.
The church is there first and then a community grows up around it.
So that was called the Town of Concord.
Yeah.
And I'll be mentioning too, a lot of these towns were popping up in the mid 1800s that
or in before that, that Concord, Massachusetts was one of the most famous towns in the US
at the time for some time.
Does that resonate with you still?
Yeah.
I think Concord has always punched above its weight.
I mean, it's only a 17,000 people here.
Yeah.
But in terms of its two different revolutions.
Sure.
And so many people, it's interesting.
Right now, if you go to many of these Concords, I would ask, where did your town get its name?
And they go, I don't know.
And I said, well, have you ever heard of Concord, Massachusetts?
No.
Battle of Lexington Concord, drawing a blank.
So you know, history isn't, this history isn't taught as thoroughly as it used to be in the
19th century.
And up until the Civil War, of course, this was the most important war in American history.
Sure.
And then the Civil War happened and that kind of super, obviously superseded the Revolutionary
War in terms of its social impact on the country.
Right.
But there's, I think the idea of both the revolutionary spirit that happened in this
town, but also that this was a fairly famous town for Ralph Waldo Emerson.
Some of the places, Concord in New York on Staten Island is actually named Concord because
Ralph Waldo Emerson's brother lived there, William Emerson.
And Henry David Thoreau used to, went there and taught, but they renamed the town after
this town because Ralph Waldo Emerson was probably, probably the most famous person
in America who wasn't a politician.
Sure.
Because I'm trying to think at that time the sports stars, they didn't have the movie,
no movie stars.
Yeah, yeah.
There were actors like the Booth family and other people, but, and the military people
were famous too.
But I think overall in terms of impact, Emerson had the greatest impact of anybody back in
that time period.
So there are a lot of these towns sprung up around that time.
Yeah.
Well, I thought I read the entry about New York too and it was funny to me coming off
of the two episodes I've done with Richard Smith about Thoreau and getting to know him
a little bit that it was not shocking to me at all to hear him write to Ralph Waldo Emerson
and say, I've been into New York a few times and it's not for me.
I'm coming home.
Yeah, it was, I think he, it's interesting because he did his walking there.
Yeah.
He walked everywhere and he walked kind of the breadth of, length and breadth of Staten
Island and much of the city, but it just didn't sing to him and he wanted to get back to the
woods of concrete.
Yeah.
Is the largest concrete, Concrete California?
Concrete California is a bedroom community of San Francisco and it's actually a place
that's affordable.
The people, at least it was when I was there, saw a lot of teachers, firefighters, those
type of people lived in Concrete and it's, I think around, I'm going to guess here, 350,000
dollars.
Oh, wow.
Okay.
Yeah.
Usually if I Google.
I could be off.
I should have just Googled that before I spotted that number.
Yeah.
I'm not sure if that's the right name, but it's around that.
And then the next largest is Concrete North Carolina.
Okay.
Which is a, which is kind of being absorbed by the mass of Charlotte, North Carolina.
The Charlotte Speedway is actually in Concrete, North Carolina and they're very fussy about
that.
It's like Concrete Motor Speedway.
It's a famous one.
Yeah.
So that's where the home of NASCAR is.
Yep.
And the North is where it's Concord everywhere else, not Concord.
Right.
So down there, if you say Concord, they say, what are you talking about?
Yeah.
Well, they, they, different pronunciations, different accents.
I've, I've, I've learned a wide array of them in my 43 years on earth here.
Yeah.
In the North, it's all Concord, but everywhere else.
I mean, I feel like we don't have enough time for two syllables, you know, Concord.
Yeah.
No, it's Concord.
It's a waste of energy.
Yeah.
I know.
Usually when I Google something about Concord, Massachusetts, if I just put Concord in instead
of without the MA, a lot of times it'll pull up the Concord, California weather or the
Dunkin' Donuts or whatever, or whatever I'm looking for.
If I don't have my location on.
It's got funny stories with that where they'll, they'll have pizza deliveries going out from
Concord, California and it doesn't quite get there.
Doesn't quite get there.
Oh, that's great.
Now we had a meeting with the mayor of Concord to set up.
My son came with us.
Actually, we took our whole family out to San Francisco for a Christmas vacation.
And so my son, who's a videographer, came to take some pictures.
And as he's walking with all of his camera equipment, there's another guy with bigger,
more powerful camera equipment coming in beside us.
And so they, camera guys started talking with each other.
It turns out it was the mayor's first day in office.
Oh, wow.
Concord, California.
We were there for his first day.
So they filmed us and filmed him.
And then they heard our story and what we were doing and traveling around and meeting
people in Concord, California.
And they said, let's follow you around instead of the mayor.
That's great.
We ended up on the news that day instead of the mayor got.
Did he have second billing?
No, he didn't even get on.
Oh, no.
So we had, it was, it was a great, that was a great introduction.
That's awesome.
And I know we were texting before I came over and there were three, you filtered down to
two, there were three questions you were going to ask people in the different Concords.
I want to ask them to you about Concord, Massachusetts.
What's the best part about living in Concord, Massachusetts?
Let me go back a step.
Okay.
Just tell you a little bit about why I asked these questions.
And then I'll answer the question because I was thinking about that myself.
Because of the randomness of the project, right?
Yeah.
There's nothing that really connects things, all these things together.
My daughter, who's a sociologist said, you have to have some definitive questions that
you ask everybody.
And that'll help you filter out or group together different ideas and different themes.
So much of the country, you can see why people are frustrated and why people are upset.
You go out to some of these places and you can find the falling down barns.
You can see the rusted out cars.
You can see needles in the street, that kind of thing.
You can see the signs of why life is tough.
Yep.
And I would say maybe three quarters of the places I've been to had better days.
Sure.
One quarter of them are doing well or actually life is getting better.
But I would say at least three quarters of them are, life is getting worse.
So I really decided I have to try and find the things that are good about these places,
and joyful about these places.
So I always start off with that question.
What's the best part about living in your Concord?
And that generally gives them an opportunity to find something that's optimistic about
their town.
And then the second question is how has it changed?
And that almost always gives them an opportunity to talk about what's bad about their town
without me delving into it, without me bringing it right to the surface.
I let them do it.
So what is the best thing about Concord?
It's actually, we're so lucky that there are so many different good answers to that question.
And I think I'll try and answer it in light of some of the other places I've been to.
First of all, it's a healthy town.
It has three downtowns really.
If you see downtown Concord, the Depot, and West Concord, those are three vibrant centers.
Now there's challenges.
There are stores that are open in the downtown and in the Depot area.
But most small towns of 17,000 people, their downtown is gone.
There's nothing there anymore.
There's a pawn shop.
There's an ATM.
And just rows and rows of boarded up storefronts.
It's really quite sad.
And outside the town there's a Dollar General or two.
And that's it.
So that's one thing I love about this town is it has a really vibrant downtown.
It has such an interesting history, of course, going back to 1635.
And people appreciate that history.
And they also, one of the things that I really love about this town is the vigor with which
we defend open spaces.
There are so many towns in the greater Boston area.
I grew up in Wilesom.
There's no open spaces left in Wilesom, except for Wilesom College and along the Aqueduct
in Wilesom.
They've developed everything because it raises their tax base and tax revenue or whatever.
Here we've maintained, we value all this open space.
So much of it has been donated and it's preserved either by the trustees or by the town or,
of course, the National Park.
So I love that part about the town.
I think that also engenders a certain spirit in the town of volunteerism and so many passionate
people working on different projects in the town.
I've been absolutely struck by that since I volunteered in the winter for working with
the 250th.
How I was a little, my reasons to do it far outweighed my hesitations.
My hesitations were, is this going to be parks and rec and we're not going to actually
do anything?
But then I met the people who are involved with this already and one, they said, oh,
you've been here for four or five years.
Welcome.
Welcome home.
And I just felt welcome.
I mean, that's a big deal to me.
And there are people involved with this that have been here for many generations.
And I think that that struck me as it's a town that has a very rich history and the
people I've met have been very welcoming of newcomers, at least so far, I'm sure.
I'm sure as I go, I'll run across some others, but it's been really incredible.
And I think this town is among the most engaging that I've ever lived in.
It's been really wonderful.
So the second question I ask is how has it changed?
And there hasn't been that much change in the town overall.
I think it has been a little bit yuppie-fied.
There's definitely a hollowing out of middle class in Concord.
You really, it's not so much of an age thing as a wealth matter.
For a while there, it seemed to be like not too many young families were moving into town.
Now in the last five years, I seem to feel like there's a new generation coming into
the town with younger people, at least in my neighborhood.
I'm now the old guy in the neighborhood.
So that's, now the one problem with that is I don't think this younger generation has
the same dedication to volunteerism that I've seen in other, the previous generation.
For instance, like they have to, I believe they have to hire in soccer coaches now.
Where in the past it was just dad would volunteer, mom would volunteer.
And there's a lot less of that apparent participation in the kids' lives.
Not to say there isn't some of that, but I feel like there isn't quite the same level.
I could see that as a teacher.
Events that used to be run by parents just trying to get people to do some work on some
of that stuff was harder.
Interesting.
Not that it didn't happen, it just became more difficult and maybe less rich in terms
of the participation.
The one obvious glaring drawback in town is a lack of racial diversity.
It's something that I've been involved with since the, really since I moved into town
trying to see what can be done.
When I got my job at Fenton, I said, oh, this is great.
I'm so glad to get my job, but you really should have hired a black guy or a black woman
to do this because you need it at this school.
You don't have diversity.
Well, when I left, the same questions were being asked.
For twenty-three, twenty-four years, it's been a struggle and a very active struggle.
It's not like we've been really trying to find solutions to this and trying to get this
town a more welcoming town.
That's one of the reasons I got very much involved with Robin's House and then Friends
of Ellen.
It's interesting, guys.
I never talk politics when I travel.
I can't.
I know that there's a lot of... I'm surrounded in a red state estate and I've got Massachusetts
plates on my car.
I'm pretty used to not talking politics with strangers, but in my town, it's harder to
not talk a little bit about the important values of this town.
I think in terms of at least the ideals that the groups here have been effective, I would
say from my perspective of not effective in changing demographics here yet, but in terms
of raising awareness and importance of it, I've talked to several high school seniors
who I do interviews for my alma mater when they're interviewing for admission.
In the course of every conversation I've had with a Concord student who's applying, that
issue has come up as something very important to them in their lives.
I think that the work that the town has done the last few years has been... It's a slow
climb.
It's a slow boulder to move up that mountain, but I do believe that the town has been effective
in at least bubbling up the importance of these ideas and how to actually make a population
shift happen.
I don't think anybody knows how to actually do that.
It's difficult.
It's very difficult.
It goes back to that other point, that it's so damn expensive to live here in most cases.
Anyway, it won't be solved in my lifetime.
I like the construct of those questions and how it actually reflect on the town you're
living in.
The third question was, how did your Concord get its name?
Many places never knew how they got their name, so I would end up doing the work beforehand
online.
I'd often drop off at a local library because you can't find... There's a lot of stuff
that still isn't on Wikipedia, believe it or not.
I would stop in the local library, look into the local history, and there'd be some yellowing
pamphlet talking about the early days of the town and the community.
That's how I got a lot of my early information was just dropping by libraries.
This town, it's interesting.
If you look it up on Wikipedia, it says it's because of the Concord or the peaceful agreement
and harmony between the first settlers and the native peoples here.
I've heard that it's incorrect.
I don't think it's right.
There's no way it's correct.
Well, that's always what it's been told, but I really feel like it was the agreement or
the Concord between the settlers before they came out here.
That's what I heard from... They really had to have some discipline in how they were going
to live their lives and the messaging that they were going to have once they settled
here.
Life was so, so tough those first few winters in particular that you couldn't have disparate
voices.
You couldn't have disagreements.
You had to work together.
You had to have a Concord amongst the people.
That would seem to make more sense as being fact.
I'm going to go with that one is the one I blame.
Is there anything that I haven't covered?
I think I read most of the articles on your site.
I picked the ones that resonated most with me.
Are there any that I've missed that you'd want to talk about?
Well, it's interesting.
Some of the longer, bigger, more places where I gather so much information are the hardest
to write about.
There's just too much information.
Then there's others where there's so little information, but if you find a little bit,
you can start digging into it.
I was able to discover actually two stories of lynchings that have never been reported.
There's a museum down south now of all the lynchings.
Neither of these lynchings.
Peaceful, harmonious Concord where we're recording.
Those stories are really horribly rich.
I don't know if you could write a novel about either one of those lynchings.
The best thing is just go out and meeting people and getting a pulse of the country.
I really had a sense of the rise of Trump before it happened.
These are not stupid people.
These are not people who are doing it because they're brainwashed.
They turned to Trump because their lives were not as good as their parents' lives.
They needed change and there was no change.
No politician offered anything that presented hope to them.
They rolled the dice.
Whether the MAGA movement has brainwashed them since, well, yeah, I think so.
Again, I don't want to get into politics on this, but it is really interesting just to
be able to go out and hear from people and see people and see their lives and see their
...
Yeah.
I think that we're in a bubble from a lot of different ways.
One of those bubbles is just what you're talking about now.
When I go back home, the town I grew up in, we actually moved from Michigan.
My dad is an auto worker.
He worked at the Saturn plant that was set up there.
Well, Saturn doesn't exist anymore.
It's a factory that still makes some parts, but it's nowhere near the production that
it used to be.
My high school class of 400, it's half that now in my high school and the entire STEM
faculty quit last year.
The problems there are so much different than the problems we have here.
You go down there and you talk to them and I just hear my friends just talk about their
everyday lives and what's going on.
It's completely different from what we talk about here.
That story is interesting because it's like the story of so many industries and so many
towns on fast forward.
They set up a factory.
This is going to be the great economic driver in Tennessee, this new automobile plant.
It was an operation, what, four or five years, maybe more?
Gone.
Poof.
It's contracted, but the town has been somewhat lucky in that Nashville has become so expensive
that it's now commuter town from my hometown to Nashville.
The town, I think, has not been as eclectomically devastated as some of the parts of the towns
you've seen or that I've driven through.
I think there's a fascinating story down there to tell just from the initiation of the Saturn
plant in the 80s until today, just what happened there.
It's also a very historic town.
There's a James K. Polk presidential house there.
There's several battle sites all around, like Battle of Franklin.
All of that is all around where I grew up.
There's quite a lot of history, quite a lot of pride in the hometown.
We have here, but then there's just big differences too.
I think it'd do people a lot of good to see these different parts of the US and just realize
how different they are.
I have not logged on Facebook in a long time, thankfully, but during 2020 it was fascinating
to see half my friends from Massachusetts, half my friends from growing up in Tennessee
and the absolute complete disconnect on what they were talking about through all this.
And then also through COVID, the complete disconnect of what people were doing during
that time.
It's really, really fascinating.
Yeah, and I've got to add one more thing.
I have met so many nice people.
Oh, absolutely.
There are so many people who I... I've gotten more and more courageous about this.
I'll go up to some dude on a Harley and he's all decked out in his black leather and he's
got his beard and looks like he hasn't washed for a week or two.
And I, you know, are you from Concord?
Yeah.
What do you want?
I said, well, I'm doing this project and I give him a little spiel and he look at me
and go, that's cool.
Yeah.
And then tell me about his life and tell me about what's the best part about his living
in Concord and how things have changed.
I think that interaction you described is in a nutshell, you approach someone and someone
who doesn't know where you're from, you're from an unknown, they're just going to be,
your first reaction is to be defensive.
I want to defend what I know, what my identity is.
And I think that's what creates discord is that people don't...
I like how you put in discord.
Discord instead of Concord.
Yeah.
So because until you can visit a town, but until you actually engage with somebody and
actually bring the guard down and talk to them, you can't understand where you are.
I'm not trying to make any real judgment about any of these places.
I mean, even if I'm there three or four days, what's three or four days in terms of judging
people's lives and all that.
But you don't have to judge...
I'm just trying to find stories and...
I mean, you're finding perspective too.
That's not judging.
That's still perspective.
I like that.
And finding perspective.
The one thing I wish I was better at, I wish I had better Spanish because again, I try
my best not to just talk to middle-aged white guys.
I mean, I try not to be a creep and talk to a bunch of little girls.
I do talk to young ladies and usually with their parents' permission or something like
that.
But I try to force myself to get out of my comfort zone and talk to... try and find
stories that I don't know about.
I don't know what your life is like.
It's a great open-ended question of what's important to you.
Going to Concord, Idaho, the most important issue in Concord, Idaho was wolves, the resettlement
of wolves into the area.
What?
As somebody who likes ecology, I'd heard about this project of reintroducing the wolf into
the wilderness of the Northwest.
But their life has been devastated by these wolves being introduced there because their
lives were all about guiding and hunting and all the prey have disappeared.
The moose have gone, the deer have gone, the elk have gone.
Why were the wolves reduced?
Just because they become endangered there or was it because...
Because they've been wiped out and there was no apex predator.
The idea being that you're going to have healthier herds if they're culled by nature, right?
If that wolf is taking the sick one and the old one and leaving the healthy animals to
pass on their genes.
It's better for the ecosystem.
In principle, that's true, but they introduced the wrong type of wolf.
You've got these wolves that are as big as a motorcycle and some of them are just killing
for fun.
Oh my gosh.
I won't get into the details of what they do, but this was the number one issue to them.
The number two issue was gold mining.
Number three issue was mercury in their rivers.
There were five different issues I remember and none of them had anything to do with me
except for I like salmon and I have a gold ring.
Those were the issues, they're day to day issues in their lives that were most important.
That's fascinating.
It's something you would have never expected to run across without doing this.
No.
Yeah.
That's an incredible project.
It sounds like you've really uncovered far more than you even anticipated.
See what I uncover in Concord, Nebraska.
I can't wait to hear.
There's bound to be some corn involved.
There's bound to be some corn.
I'll try not to make a corny story.
I have one last question for you.
Sure.
I like to ask a question from the perspective of 50 years from now when someone in the Concord
300th is listening.
I'm going to go away from towns because I know you're a big soccer fan.
Will the U.S. men's team win a World Cup in the next 50 years?
Honestly, I hope not.
Really?
Yeah.
I love soccer.
I love watching the U.S. team play.
I love going to the European Championships and going to the World Cup.
But I love the fact that there's just this one sport that the rest of the world is that
much better at than we are.
No matter how much money we put into coaching and other things, I want us to get better.
I love the quality of the game, the quality of the women's game.
Oh my gosh.
You see middle school kids doing tricks we could never do as adults.
The quality of the game is fantastic.
I just kind of like the idea that the African nations are now dominating, are starting to
dominate, are going to be dominating the World Cup and are going to be dominating the soccer
scene going forward.
Asian countries and of course the Europeans just live for it.
The Germans just love it.
Every storefront there's soccer balls in the store.
I was mentioning to you before that my wife and I went to see the Real Madrid Barcelona
game in Madrid this year.
I've been in some good El Clásico.
I've been in some good crowds before.
This was completely electric the entire time.
What's his name?
Bellingham scored the goal in the 91st minute to win it.
The thing I found really interesting, so if I go to a Patriots game or a Southlakes game
or a Bruins game, there's a goal scored and everyone stands up and you high five everyone
next to you.
When I was there I noticed nobody actually interacted with the person next to them.
They were all putting all their energy to the team on the field.
Interesting.
They start singing these songs.
I'm getting chills thinking about it, just how invested they are in these teams.
There's no atmosphere like a year.
I've gone to a Premier League match too and there's no atmosphere like a soccer team in
Europe.
The closest thing you get to it is a game seven Celtics Lakers.
That's about it.
That's as close as you get.
This happens twice a year.
That's what I was telling somebody.
Real Madrid Barcelona was like, if Yankees red sox happened once a year or twice a year.
The spectacle was pretty incredible.
I don't think the U.S. will want it.
I don't know.
It's a bit tongue in cheek when I'm saying I wouldn't want it.
I get that.
I'm rooting for them wholeheartedly when they're playing.
There's something about the fact that we're always striving to get better at it and never
quite getting there.
Let's see them advance far enough to knock out.
That would be kind of cool.
Absolutely.
Cool.
Well, thank you so much for joining.
This has been a really fun episode.
I hope the listeners 50 years from now really enjoy it.
I enjoyed it too.